Samarth Sanjay Joshi

ENGINEER (SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT)

samarthjoshi1608@gmail.com

+49 152 14041882

• Saarbrucken, Saarland, Germany

in linkedin.com/in/samarth-joshi-3b1a7218b

Profile

A Master's student in Computer Science with a focus on designing and developing digital experiences. I combine skills in user experience design and software development to create practical solutions that meet both user needs and technical requirements. I have experience working through all stages of product development, from research and wireframing to building interfaces and systems. I also have experience with cloud infrastructure and data systems, providing a balanced approach to creating efficient solutions.

WORK EXPERIENCE

06/2024 – present Saarbrucken, Germany

Research Assitant

Universität des Saarlandes, Saarbrucken, Saarland

- Contributing to an interdisciplinary AI-in-Education research initiative, with a focus on enhancing digital learning experiences.
- Actively involved in course development and instruction for Data Visualization and **Tableau**, guiding students in translating complex data into intuitive visual formats.
- Designed and created an interactive dashboard to track and highlight current AI trends in education.
- Collaborated closely with faculty and students to align research outputs with educational needs.
- Worked simultaneously on fullstack development, building scalable and user-friendly
 web applications with tech stack React, Typescript, ASP .NET, and SQL, ensuring
 seamless integration between frontend and backend systems.

01/2024 - 03/2024 Delhi, India

Data Analyst Intern

PrepInsta Pvt ltd, Delhi, India

- Worked on various data analysis and visualization projects using Python (Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly), increasing data insights accuracy by 35%.
- Created visually appealing and interactive dashboards with Tableau, leading to a 25% reduction in decision-making time for stakeholders by providing clearer data representations.

09/2023 - 01/2024 Bangalore, India

Software Developer Intern

Huawei Technologies Private Limited, Bangalore, India

- Focused on input validation, bug fixing, and thorough testing, reducing system errors and bugs by 20%, ensuring a seamless user experience.
- Delivered optimized, efficient code for both backend and frontend, improving application performance and responsiveness by 10%.

08/2023 – 09/2023 Mumbai, India

UX Research And Design Intern

Suven Consultants and Technology Pvt Ltd, Mumbai,India

- Conducted usability testing with 150+ users, iterating on design insights to enhance user engagement and interface satisfaction.
- Applied user feedback to improve overall usability, refining design based on actual user behavior improving adaptiblity for 200+ actual end users.

07/2022 - 08/2023 Pune. India

System Engineer (Information Technology)

Tata Consultancy Services, Pune, India

- Collaborated with **British Telecom** and financial institutions to resolve issues, reducing system downtime by 35% across client systems.
- Contributed to system updates and performance checks across middle east, europe, asia and north america regions, improving client system stability by 30% and minimizing defects.

EDUCATION

2024 – Present Master's Degree- Computer Science/Informatik

Saarbrucken, Germany Universität des Saarlandes, Saarbrucken, Saarland

2018 - 2022 Bachelor of Engineering (Computer)

Pune, India

Savtribai Phule Pune University, Pune, India

Bachelor Thesis: Training And Placement Portal

Developed a web-based portal to streamline job placement and industrial training processes. The system is actively used by the university, with over 500 students enrolled. Demonstrated full-stack development, user-centric design, and deployment skills.

SKILLS

Programming

Python, Java, C#, C++, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, C

Web & UI/UX Tools

Figma, Adobe XD, UI/UX Design, Responsive Web Design, Miro

Data & Visualization

Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly, Tableau

Concepts & Methodologies

Software Development Lifecycle (SDLC), Object-Oriented Programming (OOP), Agile, User-Centered Design, Machine Learning Frontend and Backend

React.js, Next js, ASP .NET, MongoDB, SQL, Prisma, Node JS, Express JS,

Cloud Platforms & DevOps

Microsoft Azure, Git, GitHub,

Software & Productivity Tools

MS Office (Excel, Word, PowerPoint), VS Code, IntelliJ, Postman

LANGUAGES

English German

C1 - Expert A2 - Basic Proficiency

Actively learning and enrolled in ongoing coursework and committed to achieving B2/C1

proficiency.

CERTIFICATES

- Microsoft Azure administrator associate (AZ-104)
- Figma UI/UX web design and animation with six projects by Udemy
- Python for data science and Big data foundations-1 by IBM
- Big data analytics with Hadoop and Apache spark by Linkedlin Learning
- ullet Foundations of user experience (UX) design by Google
- Introduction to IT Artificial Intelligence by Coursera
- Google IT support by Coursera

Organisations

Rotaract Club of Mid-East NGO, Pune, India

Associate Member

Led initiatives for over 10,000 beneficiaries including school refurbishments and food drives.

Educoin NGO, Nashik, India

Supported health and education projects impacting 5000+ children under poverty.